A Guide to the George Collins Papers, 1952-1993
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
George Collins Papers, 1952-1993
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2003-012
2.0 cu. ft. 3 boxes, 1 oversize folder
These papers are comprised mostly of correspondence from George B. Collins' time as Chairman of the Brookhavens Cosmotron Department. The collection also contains travel vouchers, research proposals, travel reports, and materials relating to Collins' work as a professor at University of Notre Dame and at Virginia Tech.
Collins, George
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired by Special Collections in 2003.
Biographical Note
George Collins, a physicist, particle experimentalist, educator, and administrator, earned a PHD with R.W. Wood at Hopkins studying UV Spectroscopy. Collins was a Professor at Notre Dame working on nuclear excitation and disintegration. He was responsible for the construction of a nuclear accelerator for the Notre Dame Nuclear Physics lab in 1935. He worked with Dr. Jose Caparo. In 1935, the accelerator was Notre Dames largest nuclear physics- related project to that date. The accelerator was the source of several decades research on nuclear physics, much of which was headed by Collins. At MIT he assisted the war effort in the Radiation Laboratory, developing radar for military purposes. He taught at University of Rochester and served the Department of Physics as Chairman. He was in charge of construction and operation of the 240 MeV synchrocyclotron and initiated, with Robert Marshak the Rochester Conferences. He was Chairman of Brookhaven's Cosmotron Department and a Fulbright fellow in Belgium. Late in his career he came to Virginia Tech and taught physics from 1968 to 1976.
Scope and Content
The collection contains a variety of materials, but consists primarily of Collins' correspondence from the 1950s through the 1970s, including his time as a professor at Virginia Tech. Other materials include professional papers, notes from speeches and papers, and travel reports. The collection includes a few photographs, as well as memorabilia from his time teaching at Notre Dame.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series. Series I: Correspondence includes letters from 1952-1993. Series II: Papers contains materials from Collins' teaching and professional career. Series III: Artifacts consists of larger memorabilia (a photograph, a sign, and a poster).
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books were removed and cataloged for the Special Collections Rare Book Collection:
"Astronomy and Cosmology- A Modern Course" by Fred Hoyle
"The Big Bang- The Creation and Evolution of the Universe" by Joseph Silk
"The Great Design- Particles, Fields, and Creation" by Robert K. Adair
"How to Tell the Birds From the Flowers" by Robert Williams Wood
"Physics for Poets" by Robert H. March
"Physics for Society" by W.B. Phillips
"University Physics- Sixth Edition" by Francis W. Sears, Mark W. Zemansky, and Hugh D. Young
Index Terms
Persons:
Collins, George
Subjects:
Faculty; Physics; Science and Technology; University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Occupations:
Physicists
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - 1952 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - 1956 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - 1957 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - 1958 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - 1959 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - 1960 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - 1963 (3 folders) (Box-folder 1-8 to 1-10)
  - 1964 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-11 to 1-12)
  - 1965 (4 folders) (Box-folder 1-13 to 1-16)
  - 1966 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-17 to 1-18)
  - 1967 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-19 to 1-20)
  - 1968 (4 folders) (Box-folder 1-21 to 1-24)
  - 1969 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-25 to 1-26)
  - 1970 (4 folders) (Box-folder 1-27 to 1-30)
  - 1971 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-31 to 1-32)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 1-33)
  - 1973 (Box-folder 1-34)
  - 1974 (Box-folder 1-35)
  - 1975 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - 1976 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - 1979 (Box-folder 1-38)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 1-39)
  - 1983 (Box-folder 1-40)
  - 1984 (Box-folder 1-41)
  - 1993 (Box-folder 1-42)
- Papers
  - The American Physical Society Nomination For Fellowship- Blank Forms (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Annual Reports by Collins Group (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Budget Justification Schedules, 1965, 1966 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - "Climates of Virginia" By Curtis W. Crockett, United States Department of Commerce Publication, 1971 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia Employee Group Hospitalization and Medical-Surgical Program Sample Enrollment Form, 1972 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - "Computer Controlled Systems" by George Collins (Box-folder 2-6)
  - George B. Collins Resume and Curriculum Vitae (Box-folder 2-7)
  - "Increasing the Physics Output of the A.G.S" by George B. Collins (Box-folder 2-8)
  - "Interpretation of Highly Inelastic Proton- Proton Interactions at 10, 20, and 30 BeV/c" by E.W. Anderson and George Collins (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Manuscript for 1992 Speech at Notre Dame (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Photographs, N.d. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Proposal ISR at CERN, 1971 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Reference Forms for Students by G.B. Collins (Copies) (Box-folder 2-13)
  - "Report on Foreign Travel" November 1965 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - "Report on Trip of George B. Collins to Russia and Europe," July 11 1958 to August 1 1959 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - "Report on Visit to Institute of Atomic Physics at Bucharest, Romania" by George Collins and Rodney Cool (Box-folder 2-16)
  - "Research Proposal to the Division of Research of the Atomic Energy Commission" University of Massachusetts, Amherst (Box-folder 2-17)
  - "Revision of Proposal to Search for Multigamma From Magnetic Monopole Pairs (Box-folder 2-18)
  - "Search for Multiphoton Events From Proton- Nuclei Interactions at 300 GeV/c+- A Submission for Physical Review" (Box-folder 2-19)
  - "The Small Distance Frontier" by George B. Collins (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Travel Vouchers (Box-folder 2-21)
  - University of Notre Dame Class Record Book 1933-1940 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - W. Peter Trower- Resume, Curriculum Vitae, and Press Biography (Box-folder 2-23)
- Artifacts
  - "No Smoking" sign. Signed by George Collins, n.d.
  - Framed photograph of Collins and physics colleagues. Pictured from left to right is A. Salam, Robert F. Bacher, Isidor Rabi, George Collins, and W.M. Powell. N.d.
  - University of Notre Dame Nuclear Physics Reunion Poster, 1992 (Folder 1)